A Guide to the Papers of the Janney and Related Gilmour and Pollock Families 1695(1755-1944)1981
Special Collections Department, University of Virginia Library
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Papers of the Janney and Related Gilmour and Pollock Families, 1695(1755-1944)1981
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
8409-a, -b, -c
This collection consists of ca. 2750 items.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
Accession #8409-a was purchased by the Library on April 23, 1990 from Jerry N. Showalter, Bookseller, of Ivy, Virginia. The collection was previously on deposit in the Southern Historical Collection at the University of North Carolina. Subsequent accessions #8409-b and #8409-c were purchased by the Library on June 24, 1991 and August 3, 1992, from Timothy Bakken, of Halvor Americana, Clarendon Hills, Illinois.
Biographical/Historical Information
John Janney, born November 8, 1798, was the son of Elisha and Mary (Gibson) Janney of Loudoun County. Janney played a large part in the development of Loudoun County, and was one of the leading attorneys in Virginia. He married Alcinda "Alice" S. Marmaduke on January 26, 1826, and became a citizen of Leesburg where he made his home for the remainder of his life. Although he did not take a very active part in politics, he was so well regarded by his fellow Whigs that he was drafted on several important occasions. He was a member of the Virginia Assembly as delegate from Loudoun County, and was a Whig elector in the presidential campaign of 1844. Janney was known for the eloquence with which he expressed the principles of his political party. He was elected a delegate to the Virginia Constitutional Convention of 1850, and, in 1860, a adelegate to the Secession Convention of 1861, then being elected by the Union men as president of the Convention. Janney opposed secession, however he accepted the adoption of the ordinance of secession when it was passed in April 1861. He continued to be an important influence on Virginia politics until his death on January 5, 1872.
Robert Stevenson Janney, born September 22, 1915, was the son of Abram David Pollock and Lucy (Stevenson) Janney. He received his education from Princeton University and was awarded the New York Herald Prize for his thesis on "Foreign Policy of the United States 1930-37." From August 1937 to spring 1938 he took a trip around the world, sailing around Europe, India and Asia. In 1937 he made 2nd lieutenant R. O. T. C. in the United States Field Artillery, and in July 1941 transferred to the Army Air Force and became 1st lieutenant. He trained at bases in Georgia, Louisiana, Alabama and South Carolina. He received his wings at Moody Field, Valdosta, Georgia in July 1942. Following intensive training in Light Bomb Group, he was made Captain, and in January 1943, he flew the South Atlantic and took part in the North Africa Campaign. In Italy he was with the 27th Fighter Bomber Group 12th Army Air Force as Group Operations Officer. During February to July 1943 he flew missions over Casablanca, Oran, Algiers and Tunis; from July until August 1943, he was stationed on Malta and then in Sicily. He was promoted to Major in November 1943. He was killed on a mission over Cecina, Italy on January 16, 1944. He received the Air Medal with three oak clusters and the Purple Heart award.
Scope and Content Information
This collection consists of ca. 2750 items, 1695(1755-1944)1981, pertaining to the Janney and related Gilmour and Pollock families, and includes personal correspondence, political correspondence and papers including broadsides, financial and legal papers, genealogical material, and photographs. Persons represented include John Janney (1798-1872); Robert Stevenson Janney (1915-1944); Abraham David Pollock and Nancy Lee (Janney) Gilmour (1886- ); Charles Phillips Janney (1839-1925); Lilias Janney (1874- ); Thomas Gordon Janney (1870- ); Abram David Pollock and Lucy (Stevenson) Janney; and, various members of the Gilmour, Janney and Pollock families.
Papers of John Janney
The papers of John Janney include biographical material, personal correspondence, political correspondence and papers, and financial and legal papers.
There are Civil War correspondence and papers of John Janney and Alcinda "Alice" S. (Marmaduke) Janney. There is a pass, June 5, 1861, for James C. Janney to go through the lines at Harper's Ferry. On August 22, 1861, John Janney, Leesburg, writes to [Joseph Eggleston] Johnston (1807-1891), Manassas Junction, about the illness of his servant "George" who drove his team to the Junction, offers fifty acres of hay, and requests that his horses with the artillery be returned. There is a list dated August-September 1861 of "Sick Soldiers nursed by Mrs. John P. Smart and Mrs. John Janney." On September 10, 1861, Arthur L. Rogers, Loudoun Artillery, writes concerning the appraisement of Janney's horses and the need for horses in service. On October 25, 1862, wife of William Barksdale (1821-1863), N[arcissa] L. [(Smith)] Barksdale (d. 1875), Oakwood, near Columbus, Mississippi, writes to Alcinda Janney, reminiscing over her visit to Leesburg, and wishing she was able to avenge the wrongdoings done to Mr. Janney. She also describes the trip from Orange Court House to Huntsville, Alabama to Corinth and Columbus, Mississippi, mentioning the starving and sick soldiers encountered; and, mentions that Bayou Lara, Louisiana was burnt, that the sugar crop is large in Louisiana, that there were several marriages and births in camps, and that she has heard little news of her husband. There is a pass, November 1, 1862, Headquarters, Whipple's Division, 12th Army Corps, Hillsborough, Virginia, for James and Robert Janney to Berlin, Maryland, and return with their brother Charles. On August 4, 1865, Joseph [Eggleston] Segar (1804-1880), Washington, requests Janney's views as to the general sentiment in regard to the result of the late civil conflict and mentions President [Andrew] Johnson (1808-1875). In his letter of August 7, 1865 to Segar, Janney comments on the action of the military authority to nullify the election. There is another letter, April 1866, from Mrs. N[arcissa] L. [(Smith)] Barksdale. Columbus, Mississippi, to [Alcinda Janney], wishing to see her friends in Leesburg, mentioning her African-American servants, Matilda and John, hoping that her sons, Ethel[bert](1859-1892) and Willie [William] (1856-1877), may become such men as their father, and mentioning acquaintances, Lieutenant and Captain Tucker, of the St. George Tucker family. Mrs. Barksdale refers to the death of her husband, William Barksdale, writing "My life has been one long day of sorrow since I left Virginia, and the sun of my life set at Gettysburg" and the problems in bringing his remains home.
There are two Civil War memorandums: "Events of the War," August-September 1862 and "War Memo" June-July 1863, by Alcinda S. (Marmaduke) Janney. "Events of the War" begins with the explanation that Leesburg was first taken possession of by the Federal forces under the command of [John White] Geary on the 8th of March following the evacuation by the Confederate troops under General [Ambrose Powell] Hill, General [Richard] Griffith, Colonel [Winfield Scott] Featherston, and Colonel [William] Barksdale. In August, several Leesburg residents were arrested, including John Janney, N. Braden, Rev. Nourse, and Armistead Vandeventer. Mrs. Janney mentions Yankee soldiers entering the drugstore and peoples' homes looking for food and Colonel Geary requesting a room. She writes that the main body of troops occupied the town and a portion encamped on the "Morven" estate. Referring to March again, she writes that upon evacuation, General Hill gave orders to burn wheat stacks along Point of Rocks, Maryland, the finest mill on the Potomac, and a fine depot in the suburbs. In August, Leesburg and the surrounding area is left under Federal rule but the blockade was raised. The formation of a "Home Guard" disturbed the relative quiet, when they began to confiscate goods and arms from stores and raiding the houses of secessionists. She relates that a company of Southern cavalry arrived for the first time since March and were involved in some skirmishes with the enemy, that they met with General [William] Barksdale and Captain Doherty, and that the Southern troop left for Maryland. The "War Memo" relates the outrages committed by the Yankee troops and the conflicting news and rumors heard by civilians concerning the progress of the war. The June 28th entry finds Confederate troops on their farm procuring two old carriage horses and other necessities, causing an estimated loss of $2000 to $2500, according to [servant] "George"; the two old carriage horses were apparently returned at the insistence of "an old colored free woman." The June 29th entry mentions the Eleventh Corps under General [Oliver Otis] Howard being encamped on the portion of the Janney farm taken care of by [Thomas] Havener and committing outrages and that "they spoke of their deeds being justifiable because Mr. J was the President of the Va. Convention..." She writes of stories heard about various officers and their activities, including [Alexander Peter] Stewart, [Richard Stoddert] Ewell, [James] Longstreet, A[mbrose]; P[owell] Hill, and Robert E. Lee. She also mentions various places where fighting supposedly is taking place, including Point of Rocks, Maryland, Gettysburg, Pennsylvania, Vicksburg, Mississippi, and Charleston, South Carolina. The July 25th - 29th entries relate to civilian activity; mentioned are that persons are being allowed to travel safely to Washington and Baltimore without papers and the "murder" of a civilian named Mathews on the river near Whitesford.
The financial and legal papers of John Janney consist of correspondence, memorandums of agreement and other legal documents, and accounts and bills of sale pertaining to Janney's legal practice and his farm operation. Among the papers, 1832-1839, are: license to practice law in Virginia (December 24, 1829); correspondence about claims against the deceased Solomon Parsons (January 24, 1832 and September 10, 1834); opinion on the wills of John and Mary Hawling, with copies of the wills (1832); papers on Brown vs. Taylor (ca. 1832-1847); and, letter from John Sinclair, Mountsville, relating the courses and lengths of the lines and descriptions of the corners in dispute between Charles Fenton Mercer and the Skinners (January 20, 1837). Among the papers, 1841-1848, are: an account of Amos Janney and Edmund Jennings (June 8, 1841); memorandum of agreement between Alexander Kilgam and Aquila Janney re a tract of land in Loudoun County (December 20, 1844); and, a circular letter announcing the establishment of the firm N. E. Janney and Company in the china, glass, and earthenware business (April 1, 1848). There is also correspondence from the period of 1841-1848. On October 10, 1841, Barrow [Frere ?], Cottage Farm, Aldie, Loudoun County, writes concerning financial obligations with a postscript on "an improved implement for cleaning the roads." There are letters, July 20 & 22, 1846, from Benjamin B. Davis, Salem, Ohio, to Samuel M. Janney, Springdale, Loudoun County, with copies of documents, concerning the legacy of Rebecca (McArtor) Murphy from Mahlon McArtor. On May 24, 1847, Abbott Lawrence (1792-1855), Boston, writes to John [Strother] Pendleton (1802-1868), Culpeper, that the machine shop at Lowell is full, with 600 persons at work, and that a new machine shop will be opening in the new town of Lawrence, and praises the young men from Virginia working in the machine shop. On October 23, 1847, Benjamin Hawley, Salem, Ohio, writes to Samuel M. Janney, Springdale, Loudoun County, on behalf of Rebecca (McArtor) Murphy. There is a letter, October 11, 1847, from John Sinclair concerning a land dispute between Edward P. Upton and Jonathan Beard. Among the papers, 1850-1859, are: bill of sale for a "negro woman H[arriett ?] Jackson" and "to warrant her to be a slave for life" from William H. Gallagher, Morrow, Ohio, to John Janney; answer of Common Council in Council of Alexandria vs. William Wheeler (August 13, 1850); and, Abraham heirs certificates (January 1853). There is an agreement, September 30, 1850, between John Janney and Thomas Havener to hire the latter as a farmer on land owned by Janney in Loudoun County, describing the conditions. There are also a memorandum of agreement and accompanying papers, 1851-1862, between Robert Beverley and Charles C. Turner. There are documents, November - December 1859, giving power of attorney to John Morgan from Jane Morgan and others in the suit relating to the Hutchison estate. Among the papers, 1860-1870, are: papers re the Hutchison estate (April - August 1860); notes re Confederate States of America vs. Joshua Pancoast estate (July 1861); bond to John Janney from Hogan estate (December 30, 1861); and, receipts to Charles Phillips Janney from John Janney on account for the purchase of his law library (January 13 and December 18, 1869). Other items include United States Internal Revenue Service Licenses granted to John Janney of Leesburg, Loudoun County to carry on the business or occupation of lawyer (December 19, 1864 and July 10, 1866). There is also a letter, June 1, 1866, from John R. Watkins, Baltimore, concerning a suit against Matilda W. Fitzhugh of Loudoun County, in which he claims that he left $1600 in Federal money upon his capture by the Federal Army, which was spent by the Fitzhugh family.
There are financial and legal papers, 1853-1869, relating to the Alexandria, Loudoun and Hampshire Railroad Company. On January 19, 1853, John Janney, Leesburg, writes to Charles B. Ball, discussing his week's service on horseback with Captain George L. Green, engineer, making a general examination of the country from Alexandria to Harpers-Ferry, mentioning various places visited in determining the route to be established. On June 27th, Lewis McHenry, Office Alexandria, Loudoun and Hampshire Rail Road Company, writes re securing subscriptions to finance the construction of the road to Washington. There is a proposal, March 25, 1854, from Miller & Schuyler to build and equip the Railroad Company's road, exclusive of the cost of engineering and right of way, from Alexandria to its western terminus at Westernport or Piedmont. On December 22, 1854, Lewis McHenry of the Railroad Company, writes enclosing comparisons of cost to company as estimates by contractors' bids. There are numerous stock receipts, 1855-1860. On February 27, 1857, Sidney G. Miller, Alexandria, writes detailing his proposal for the entire construction and equipment of the Railroad Company's road from the depot at Alexandria to the depot at Wineberten. There are documents establishing the appointment of John Janney as director on behalf of the Board of Public Works in the Alexandria, Loudoun and Hampshire Railroad Company (December 20, 1860 and January 3, 1867). There is also a proposition, March 9, 1869, with a view to the further extension of the Railroad Company's road.
There are financial and legal papers, 1796-1842, dealing with the business of the Mutual Assurance Society. There are Declarations for Assurance for dwelling houses and other buildings in Leesburg, Loudoun County for Samuel Hough (June 1796), Lee Durham (November 1803), John Drish (January 1804), and Joseph Smith (May 1805). There is a Revaluation of Buildings declared for Assurance by Joseph Smith, signed by James Rawlings (September 26, 1816). Dated October 21, 1825 is a list of debts due to the Mutual Assurance Society "against fire on buildings of the State of Virginia for ensurance of buildings...," signed by James Rawlings. Papers of 1825 relate to a claim against John and Elizabeth Potter. There is a Revaluation of Building formerly declared for Assurance by Samuel Murray, signed by John Rutherford (October 18, 1827).
The personal correspondence of John Janney and Alcinda "Alice" S. (Marmaduke) Janney refer chiefly to family news but does contain some political references. On December 5, 1831, Alice Janney, Hillsborough, expresses her feelings on the death of her twenty-three year old daughter, Cornelia, and includes a poem dedicated to her daughter. There are two letters, April 23 and May 11, 1841, from S. H. Williams, Cumberland, Maryland, concerning family news, including the last days and death of their child Alice. Letters from John Janney and Alice Janney dated September 19, October 1 and November 3, 1848 refer to the illness of Nathaniel Ellicott Janney and the family's efforts to take him home before his death. They describe the family's journey on the steamer "Alice" on the Ohio River, the last days and subsequent death of Nathaniel Janney with his wife, Sarah [Ann Irwin] Janney, and other family by his side; and, mention the arrival of Robert H. Miller, husband of Anna [Janney Miller]. On April 24, 1851, John Janney, Richmond, writes to Alice Janney referring to mixed basis representation and the numerous politicians speaking their opinions on the subject. An April 25, 1854 letter from George Adre, Greenwood, discusses the fire that destroyed his house. On April 23, 1861, John Janney, Richmond, writes Alice Janney that there may be trouble in Washington, Richmond is full of troops, and that General Robert E. Lee was introduced in the House. There is a letter, [April 1861], from John Janney, Alexandria, to Alice Janney, with the news that Tennessee has been electing members of convention and that he is to be president of the Convention in Richmond. He also mentions the books, The Children of the Abbey and Evelina [or, The History of a Young Lady's Entrance into the World]. There is a letter, August 16, 1871, from J[ohn]; W[illiam]; M[allet](1832-1912), The Rawley Springs, Rockingham County, Virginia, to John Janney, discussing the springs with "An Analysis of The Rawley Springs in Rockingham County, Va..." printed on the verso. There are two letters, September 30 and October 10, 1880, from Thamsin Janney, Lincoln, Virginia, to Alice Janney, sending medication and giving directions for their use.
The political papers of John Janney are rich in discussions of the principles and activities of the Whig party, presidential elections, prominent politicians, and other aspects of Virginia and national politics from the 1830's until the 1860's.
There are certifications, November 1836, that a presidential and vice-presidential election was held in the counties of Loudoun, Fairfax and Fauquier. In a letter of March 26, 1838, Henry Clay (1777-1852) writes to Janney concerning the speech of John C[aldwell] Calhoun (1782-1850) which was brought to the attention of the Senate by Daniel Webster (1782-1852), Calhoun voting against the engrossment of the Sub-Treasury Bill, and hopes that the measure will be defeated in the House. Letters and documents of April 9 & 21 and May 1, 1838, concern Janney's appointment to represent the state of Virginia at all meetings of the stockholders of the Chesapeake and Ohio Canal Company in the absence of Charles J[ames] Faulkner.
During 1840 there are numerous invitations to Janney to either attend or speak at meetings, conventions and festivals in support of William Henry Harrison and John Tyler and the Whig party. A circular letter of May 30, 1840 from Clarksburg, invites the recipient to attend a convention of delegates "to aid the great cause of Reform in promoting the Election of General William Henry Harrison and John Tyler." There is a letter, June 11, 1840, from Samuel Chilton, Warrenton, written on behalf of the Central Whig Committee of Vigilance of Fauquier County; and, a letter, June 16, 1840, from G. Cuthbert Powell, Middleburg, concerning preparations for a large assemblage of people in July. A circular letter of July 13, 1840 from Wheeling, invites the recipient to attend a convention in that city to "aid the cause of Harrison, Tyler and Reform" to be held by the Whigs of the states of Virginia, Pennsylvania and Ohio. A circular letter of August 24, 1840 from Martinsburg invites the recipient to attend a public festival in the good cause of Harrison and Reform to be held by the Whigs of Berkeley County on September 10th. On August 27, 1840, Charles J[ames] Faulkner (1806-1884), Martinsburg, writes concerning his attendance at the event on September 10th. On August 29, 1840, P[hilip]; R[icard] Fendall (1794-1868), Washington, inquires about William Henry Harrison's and Martin Van Buren's militia plans. A circular letter of September 1, 1840 from Richmond, invites the recipient to attend the Whig State Convention to be held on October 5th. There is a letter, September 21, 1840, from the sub-committee of arrangements for the Whig State Convention to be held on October 5th, concerning the proposed arrangement to have a meeting of the several electors of the district on the day before the convention in order to form a college to select a president and secretary whose names will be announced by one of the electors. A circular letter of September 22, 1840 states the resolutions adopted at the September 17th meeting of the Democratic Whig Club of Norfolk concerning the plans of the Grand Whig Encampment on the Plains of York Town to be held on October 19th. There are certifications, November 1840, that a presidential and vice-presidential election was held in the counties of Loudoun and Fairfax.
There is a heartfelt letter, July 4, 1843, from Janney, Philadelphia, regretfully declining an invitation to unite with his fellow Whigs in that city, adding a sentiment on the "Cradle of American Liberty." During 1844 there are numerous invitations to attend or speak at meetings, conventions and festivals in support of Henry Clay and the Whig party. An interesting letter of February 22, 1844, from J[eremiah] Morton (1799-1898), "Moreland," Fluvanna County, discusses William ["Extra Billy"] Smith (1797-1887), J[ohn]; S[trode] Barbour (1790-1855), and his own speech on the subjects of the public debt and the bank and tariff question. On February 27, 1844, R. T. Daniel of Richmond writes as chairman of the Whig Central State Committee, to the Whig Electors in the state, making some suggestions on the gain of monies in order to publish and circulate the "Whig Address" and "Facts from the Record" and the registering of all Whig voters for the spring and fall elections by the appointment of an executive committee. A circular letter of March 9, 1844, "Young Men's Whig National Convention of Ratification. To the Young Whigs of the United States," serves as an invitation for a convention to be held on May 2nd in Baltimore. On March 9, 1844, Wyndham Robertson (1803-1888), Fluvanna County, comments at great length on an editorial in the Whig on March 5th and other articles which apparently misrepresented his own remarks and those actions passed in the Committee, and also mentions [Willoughby ?] Newton (1802- 1874), [John Caldwell] Calhoun, and [Daniel] Webster. A circular letter of July 8, 1844, Clarksburg, is an invitation to a Whig convention to be held on August 21st. A circular letter of July 1844 is an invitation to a Whig Barbecue on July 25th, along with the Whig Convention. On July 19, 1844, Willis Green (1783-1845 ?), Washington, writes putting forth suggestions for "the prominent active Whigs of the State" to "unite upon some plan to act in concert throughout the state," similar to the plan adopted by the Whigs of Ohio which involves dividing the state into districts. A circular letter of July 22, 1844, Winchester, is an invitation for a "Grand District Mass Meeting" to be held on August 22nd "for the purpose of proclaiming and enforcing the principles and designs of the Whig party." A circular letter of July 24, 1844, Charlestown, Jefferson County, is an invitation for a mass meeting or county convention for "advocates of the Whig Cause and Principles." Letters of 1844 continue to discuss the Whig party as well as the Loco- Focos. A circular letter of August 12, 1844 is an invitation for a Convention in the Whig City of Wheeling to be held on September 12th. A circular letter of August 28, 1844, Cumberland, Maryland, is an invitation for a mass meeting to be held on September 17th. On September 10, 1844, James F[rench] Strother (1811-1860), Rappahannock, writes concerning a meeting of the Whig party to be held in October. A circular letter of September 10, 1844, Williamsburg, is an invitation for a Convention at York Town on October 10th to support Henry Clay. On September 11, 1844, Alexander Hugh Holmes Stuart (1807-1891), Staunton, writes about upcoming plans including being present on October 1st when the Federal Court meets in order to make his arrangements for the continuance of his causes and traveling to New York in early October to attend the commencement of the proceedings of the Institute, and thereby regretfully declining a visit to Loudoun County. A circular letter of September 12, 1844, Martinsburg, is an invitation to address a Mass Meeting on October 10th "in defence of the great principles of our Party." A circular letter of September 20, 1844, Rockville (Montgomery County, Maryland) is an invitation to a Mass Meeting on September 30th. On September 23, 1844, Alexander Hugh Holmes Stuart, Staunton, writes again declining a visit to Loudoun County because of previous engagements and commenting on the people of Loudoun as being "the most enlightened & virtuous in Virginia." A letter from Warrenton on October 3, 1844 mentions the Loco- Focos meeting. William Cabell Rives (17932-1868), Castle Hill, writes on October 7, 1844 that he is unable to attend the gathering of the Whigs in Loudoun County due to ill health. On October 7, 1844, James F[rench] Strother, Rappahannock, writes concerning meetings of the Whig party. There are certifications, November 6-11, 1844, that presidential elections were held in the counties of Rappahannock, Loudoun, Fauquier, Fairfax and Culpeper. There is an interesting letter of November 28, 1844, from John S[trother] Pendleton (1802-1868), "Redwood," Culpeper, which mentions a conversation with Samuel Chilton about his being a candidate for re-election to the Congress, inquires of Janney whether he would accept such a nomination, and comments that public sentiment seems to be leaning toward Janney or himself. Pendleton's letter also includes a lengthy discussion of the future nomination and matters of consideration. There are also letters from Pendleton on December 9 and 10, 1844 concerning similar matters. On December 10, 1844, Janney writes to Pendleton concerning his inquiries on the next Congressional election and declining any nomination for himself, stating his views regarding this. Pendleton answers on December 16, 1844, commenting on Janney's letter, discussing how men in the public are sometimes urged to become a candidate, relating his regard for Janney and his own unwillingness to pursue the nomination if Janney were willing to, mentioning considerations of support from various counties, and referring to circumstances which would make a congressional term desirable to him. On December 28, 1844, J. C. Gibson, Culpeper, writes a lengthy, heartfelt political letter concerning Whigs, the Texas Whigs, Virginia, and elections and further wishes to solicit Janney's name as a candidate for this district in the ensuing election for Congress.